お招き頂きありがとうございます。とても光栄です。
ポーランドには初めて来ました。
ヨーロッパ中、旅行したんですがどういうわけかポーランドには来たことがありませんでした。
ワルシャワでの滞在をとても楽しんでいますし、とりわけこのイベントのために来れてとてもワクワクしています。
このイベントを企画して私のワルシャワ滞在を実現して頂いた事
そしてご参加くださった皆さんに大変感謝します。
私のプレゼンテーションのタイトルは“プログラム可能なお金の未来”ですが
実はこれがタイトルではありません。全部のプレゼン用のタイトルをこれにしてるんです。
なぜなら、プレゼンのだいたい２時間くらい前まで、これから話す事を決めていないからです。
なので皆さんと同じくらい、私自身がちょうど今日これから話すことが判明してびっくりする事になるんです。
では、聴衆の皆さんから少し情報をもらう所から始めたいと思います。
残念ながら（ポーランド語だったので）私の前にフィリップが話していた事が理解できなかったので。
ここにいらっしゃる方で、暗号通貨を保有している、もしくは人生のどこかで少なくとも１回は取引した事があるという方は何人いるでしょうか？
全員ですね、わかりました。
いいですね。私にとってやりやすいです。暗号通貨とは一体全体何なんだみたいな事は説明しなくて良いようです。
飛ばして本題に入れます。
今日はコミュニティについて話したいと思います。オンラインとオフラインその両方で
どのようにして面白くてエキサイティングなコミュニティを作るか。
私は人生でたくさん旅をしてきました。たくさんの異なった場所で暮らしてきました。
そして私はいつもある決まったタイプの界隈に惹きつけられている事に気づきました。
たくさんのアーティストやミュージシャンがいる場所に住むのが好きなようなのです。
風変わりな小さなコーヒーショップや
人々がライブ・パフォーマンスを行う何だか変なバーがある地域に暮らすのが好きなのです。
そこではバンドやミュージシャンやアーティストに会えます。壁にグラフティ（落書き）がある場所に暮らすのも好きです。
たぶんそういった場所、少なくとも私が住んでいた場所は、そんなに安全ではありません。
分かりますよね。少し危険ですらあります。
実際の所、しばしばその界隈では、私がこの地域で暮らす唯一の白人である事に気づくことも多かったです。
もしくは、私だけが地元民ではないかです。
でも、こうした界隈は長続きしません。
アーティストやミュージシャン、貧乏な学生たち、こうした地域に暮らしていた人々は
そういったエリアが大好きです。なぜって賃料が安いから。
なぜって地域開発がまだ起こっていないから。
なぜって、表現の機会があるからです。
おかしくて風変わりな事や、あまり安全でない環境その全てがあった事で
たくさんのちょっと変わっててクリエイティブな人たちがやって来たのです。
必然的に、そんな界隈に十分長い事暮らしていると、他の人達も気づきだします。
そしてそこは“クール”な場所になり始めます。そしてその場所が“クール”になり始めると
そうする余裕のある人々が、その界隈めがけて引っ越し始めます。
そしてますますリッチな人々がこうした界隈に引っ越しだすのです。
１年か２年後には、町の角にはスターバックスが登場します。
風変わりで奇妙なミュージシャン達みんながいたバーは、ギャラリーやブティックに取って代わられます。
以前よりちょっとだけもっと高所得者層向けの、もっと高価な衣服を売るんです。
そして賃料が値上がりし始めます。不動産価値が上がり始めます。
ほどなくして自分たちが引っ越してきた理由だったアーティストやミュージシャン、面白い人たちはみんな
そこではもう家賃が払えなくって暮らせなくなります。
そして引っ越していきます。そしてその界隈は最終的に、若いプロフェッショナル達でいっぱいに…
スーツを着て、毎朝会社に出勤し、９時から５時まで働くんです。スターバックスコーヒーを片手にね。
彼らはとっても忙しくて常に電話しています。そしてそんな地域は今や、クソみたいなもんです。
あなたはまた引っ越して、また“クール”な場所を探すんです。このサイクルの繰り返し。
“ジェントリフィケーション” アメリカではこの現象を表現するのにこの言葉を使います。
その界隈を面白くしていたあらゆる事は
そんなに長くはそこに住んでいなかった、全ての風変わりでおかしな人たちのおかげだったと分かったわけです。
そしてもし、あなたがクリエイティビティと表現活動でいっぱいの環境で暮らしたいとして
そうした環境に起こりうる最悪の事は、商品化、企業化、マーケティングです。
なぜなら、そうしたクールな何かがあったとして、そのクールで本物の何かを手に入れ
そしてそれをコカ・コーラやナイキのためのマーケティング・キャンペーに変えてしまったのなら、それはもうクールではないからです。
その時まで彼らが“クール”だと思っていたものは、もはや“クール”ではありません。
それは真正さを台無しにします。金が注ぎ込まれ、真正さの全ては失われます。
私が初めてインターネットのデジタル・コミュニティに参加したのは1980年代の中頃でした。
そうしたデジタル・コミュニティに参加するには、モデムを買わなければなりませんでした。
そして掲示板システムにダイヤルしなければなりませんでした。
この掲示板システムは、ベースメントに住んでる誰かのホビーとして運営されていました。
150人くらいの参加者がいて、彼らはちょうど私と同じくらい全員おかしなやつらでした。
他の人々には理解されない、モデムを持ってるおかしな15歳。
オンラインでの会話はとても楽しかったです。
そして90年代の終わりに向かって、掲示板システムは人気になり始めました。
大きな企業が、小規模の運営者を買収し始め、広告を打ち、会員費用を請求し始めました。
そしてコンテンツに“磨き”をかけ始め、“改善”し出します。
もうちょっとだけ、主流の人々のお口に合うようにしようとし始めます。
「言葉づかいに気を付けて。」「悪い言葉を使わないで。」「大人向けです。」「家族向けにしましょう。」
そもそも掲示板システムを面白くしていた、興味深くておかしな人々は
みんな、会話ができる他の場所を探し始めます。なぜってもう彼らはそこで歓迎されていないから。
いくつかのケースでは、金銭的に参加できる余裕がないからです。
私たちがそもそもその場へ参加した理由、クリエイティブな会話の全ては今や失われてしまったのです。
実際、その当時のこうした掲示板システムのおかしな事のひとつに
参加者は全員男ばっかりでした。
その頃の、1985年のオンライン掲示板システムの参加者に女性はいなかったんです。
でも、企業はこうした掲示板システムを、出会い系サイトにしようと努力しました。
そのために、より多くの顧客を引き付けようと、男に女性のふりをさせたのです。
そこで見るのはハンドルネームが“ヘレン”という他の男と、男が会話してる状態です。
掲示板システムへのより多くの会費を得るためにです。そうマーケティング！
面白いのは、その当時も何人かは女性参加者がいました。その女性たちは男性の名前を使っていました。
その方がもっと快適だったし、変態にびくびくする事も少なくてすんだからです。
そして企業は偽ヘレンをその偽男性名の人達に話しかけさせ、さらなる会費を支払わせようと必死で口説かせていたのです。
その時には、私はすでにUsnetに移動していました。Usnetとはグループ・ディスカッションの場で
、その当時、1980年代の終わりにかけてインターネット中で使われていました。
テキストベースのコミュニティで、インターネット上にいる
世界中の誰とでもメッセージの交換ができました。
当時、おそらく50万人くらいの人が使っていました。
Usnetはとても奇妙、ものすごーくおかしな所でした。
実際、Usnetには“alt”（代替）グループと呼ばれる特別なコーナーがあり
そのオルタナ・グループ全てにはアクセスできませんでした。でもアクセスできた場所はとても特別な場所でした。
そこにはダンジョン＆ドラゴンのファンの全員がおり、全てのコミック・ブックファン、全てのおかしなSFファン
そしてたくさんの性的なコンテンツ、変な趣味。
一般的に言って、うまく他のグループにフィットしない人たちが“alt”グループにいたのです。
そして企業がやって来ました。
彼らはUsenetを購読サービスとして運用し始めます。一番最初に切り離したのが“alt”グループでした。
今やお金を払えば、クリーンバージョンのUsenetが手に入りますが、“alt”グループはもう手に入れる事はできません。
なぜって、“alt”グループは当時、あまり礼儀正しくなかったからです。彼らはあまり協力的でもなかったし、あまりクリーンでもなかったからです。
なので彼らはUsenetをそうした変なモノ全部、奇妙なモノ全部と共に持ち去って、スーツで身なりを整えさせ、髪を切り
そうやってUsenetはつまらなくなったんです。面白い人たちは全員去っていきました。
そしてWebが始まります。Webによってクリエイティビティと表現の爆発が起こります。
始めの頃、ウェブサイトは全部おかしなものでした。多すぎる配色、点滅するタグやフォント、見た目はひどいものでした。
デザインのセンス何てありもしない。
でも、そこでの会話、そこで出会えるクリエイティビティや変わった人々は素晴らしいものがありました。
そして企業が参入してきます。彼らは全部を“磨き”あげ、“キレイ”にしていきます。「このサイトでは悪い言葉は使わないでください！」
「これは承認制コンテンツです。」
そしてCompuServeとAOLがやって来て
あらゆる汚い言葉やおかしな人々から保護され、キュレートされた環境を作り上げます。
ジェントリフィケーションは波のようにインターネット中に広まり、私たちのデジタルな領土は、あの界隈のように高級化されていきます。
そして全てのジェントリフィケーションのサイクルの結果はみな同じです。
その場所に行って、そこを面白いものにしていた人々は、もはや歓迎されません。
金銭的に参加する余裕もなく、発言する事も許されません。そして彼らは去っていきます。
そこに参加したそもそもの理由は全部、もうそこにはありません。
そうしたキュレートされた場所を後にした多くの人々は、Webの他の場所に行きました。
そして自分のウェブサイトと独立したコミュニティを立ち上げ始めました。
そしてWeb 2.0が起こります。Web 2.0が起こった時、MySpaceやそしてFacebook
そしてその他のソーシャルメディアサイトが始まりました。
彼らは非常に注意深くコンテンツをキュレーションしています。
ナチスに関するメッセージをFacebook上に投稿しても、しばらくの間はやり過ごせるでしょう。
でも、おっぱい見せてくれたら神様が助けてくれるかも！ちょっと待って！そんなのあり得ない。
ここは家庭向けの環境です！悪い言葉を使わないで。注意深くキュレートされ、たくさんのマーケティング、存分な上品化。
そして面白い人々は全員去っていきます。
今や、もしあなたがまだFacebookアカウントを持っているなら
きっとそこでは、お孫さんの写真を楽しめますね！
実際、子供たちはもうFacebookを使いたくありません。
その理由は、今では彼らの親までそこにいるからです。
そして子供たちも去っていきます。彼らはReeditや4chanに行きます。ここでもジェントリフィケーション。
ビットコインはおかしくて変なものでした。そして私は、ビットコインがおかしくて変だった時が大好きだったんです。
でも何人かの人たちにとって、ビットコインは異様すぎました。おそらく難しすぎて理解できなかった。
しかもビットコインでドラッグを買える小さな可能性があった。ただし、“良い”ドラッグではなくて。
ファイザーの作った高額なドラッグではなくて、アデロール（ADHD治療合剤・市販薬）でもなくて、これはつまり覚醒剤なんですけど。
フェンタニル（鎮痛剤・市販薬）でもなくて。まあこれはヘロインなんですけど。処方された“良い”薬ではなくて、“悪い”薬です。
マリワナみたいなね。
人々がドラッグを買えてしまう。ビットコインは企業イメージにあまり好ましくない他の事もできてしまう。
では、どうやって貨幣を“高級化”したら良いでしょうか？
どうやっておかしなモノを取ってきて、スーツで正装させ、散髪させ、役員達にプレゼンさせれば良いでしょうか？
I remember the first few years when I'd go to companies;
they'd ask me to come and present.
They would say to me, "We want you to talk to our executives, but when you talk to our executives,"
"could you please say 'blockchain'? Don't say 'Bitcoin',
because Bitcoin is weird and blockchain is the future."
And I said, "No, I won't say 'blockchain.' I will say 'Bitcoin',
because Bitcoin is the future and blockchain is bullshit."
"I'll also say 'bullshit' to your executives, because you
paid me to come here and tell you the truth as I see it."
I'm not going to try to sell you something
that's nicely packaged, just to avoid offending."
I'm interested in telling the truth.
The reason cryptocurrencies are interesting, the reason
Bitcoin is interesting, is because it's not controlled.
It can't be censored, because it's open.
A lot of the people involved are very "weird."
Weird computer geeks, weird cryptographers
who have weird ideas about privacy and freedom.
These weird people are why I'm involved in Bitcoin,
because I'm weird too and that's okay.
If you take all of that out, what you're left with
-- this blockchain -- is a sterile,
inexpressive, un-[innovative] environment.
A corporate plaything that has been sanitized of
everything interesting and left as an empty shell.
It's basically a very slow database.
If someone comes to you and [asks],
"Do I need a blockchain for my business," ask them:
"Do you need something that is open, neutral, borderless,
which no one controls and resists censorship?"
If yes, then you need Bitcoin.
Or Ethereum. Monero. Zcash.
Some open, public, blockchain cryptocurrency system
that expresses these capabilities.
But if you don't need something that's open,
borderless, neutral, censorship-resistant,
and not controlled by anyone,
what you're really asking for is a database.
So install a database. You don't need a blockchain.
If you take all of the weird people out, with them goes
all of the innovation, all of the interesting development.
If what you try to do is make business-as-usual,
only now with a blockchain...
If the purpose of introducing
this technology into your bank
is to be able to not change anything
about how you do business...
Or if your government says, "We will do a digital
currency. We heard there's a digital currency...
using 'blockchain' that is open, decentralized,
borderless, censorship-resistant, and neutral."
"We want to do just that, except we don't want it to be open, decentralized, censorship-resistant, neutral...
or borderless. We'd like that but we want it to be controlled within our borders, with the ability to control...
who has access to it, with full censorship.
We ultimately decide who has power on this system."
Also known as a database.
You can build that and it will be boring.
All of the innovation, all of the excitement, all of
the reason why I'm interested in these technologies --
and perhaps why some of you are interested in
these technologies -- is precisely because they're weird.
Precisely because they're different, because
they're open, because they allow everyone to innovate...
and express themselves creatively
in ways that we don't anticipate.
In ways that are completely unpredictable and, in
some ways, that are offensive. That's okay.
I don't want to live in a world of pastel colors, carefully
curated advertising, marketing focused tested phrases,
where you can't say the bad words.
I want to live in a world with color, with creativity,
with variety, with diversity, with ideas.
Ideas that sometimes offend me and scare me,
that I don't understand, with weird people around me...
who are free to express themselves,
because that's where creativity comes from.
It's not just Bitcoin. We're gonna see this happen again
and again. We've already gone through the phase...
where people said, "Yes, I'm interested
in blockchain, but not Bitcoin."
When someone tells you, "I'm interested in blockchain
but not Bitcoin," what they mean is "I don't understand."
Or they've heard someone else say it and
they think they can be cool if they say that too.
It's a bit like someone saying, "MySpace is so last year.
I'm into Facebook now."
It happened to Bitcoin, but it's going to keep happening.
It's going to keep happening to every cryptocurrency...
that dares to do something interesting.
Right now, the big banks and governments,
they're in love with Ethereum.
They love the fact that Ethereum has all of these
capabilities that seem much less weird than Bitcoin.
But they don't realize: all of the weirdness is still there.
I love the weirdness in Ethereum because...
quite honestly, the whole point of Ethereum is to make
unstoppable code, applications that you cannot turn off.
The reason you can't turn them off is
because they're decentralized apps, DApps.
Why make a DApp unless you wanted to
make a DApp that somebody wants to turn off,
and you wanted to continue working?
The whole point of an uncensorable application is
[writing] applications that are offensive to some people.
People are going to write applications for
Ethereum that are going to be offensive,
probably offensive to everyone in this room;
maybe a bit offensive, maybe [very] offensive.
Drug markets that cannot be shut down,
sex markets that cannot be shut down.
All of the interesting applications you can do
in a decentralized, neutral, unstoppable...
environment for code are precisely
applications that somebody wants to stop.
Those are even more powerful in the countries
where the people who want to stop them are in power.
If I'm in Russia and I want to put something on
Ethereum, I'm going to put a Pussy Riot application...
just so that I can annoy Putin.
Can't stop it.
In [China], they had a problem with
sexual assaults at campuses.
The academic institutions tried to shut up the victims; they put their stories on the Ethereum blockchain...
so that they couldn't be censored. Any speech
worth speaking offends someone, Oscar Wilde said.
Speaking the truth that somebody wants you not
to publish is journalism; everything else is marketing.
At some point to the next couple of years, someone
is going to write a weird application on Ethereum.
The big banks and all of the organizations
that today are absolutely enamored with Ethereum...
[will] go running to the Ethereum Foundation
and to the Ethereum Enterprise Alliance.
They're going to say, "Hey, we'd like you to stop this."
And the Ethereum Foundation is going to say,
most likely, "No, we won't." Or better yet, "We can't."
"Submit your Ethereum Improvement Proposal.
Let's see what the community thinks."
"Hey, community. Do you want to stop this application?
Because JP Morgan Chase doesn't like it. No? Oops."
Or maybe they decide to stop it and we get
another hard fork. Then we have three Ethereums.
Ethereum, Ethereum Classic, and Ethereum Uncensored.
Because you can't stop these things.
All you can do is fork away a bullshit corporate version.
But the other one continues to run.
Then what do you have?
That's the moment you suddenly realize:
this is the first time we have a digital
community that can't be gentrified.
You can plant your Starbucks on the corner,
but you can't kick out the weirdos.
If you try to kick out the weirdos, we fork it
and we take the neighborhood with us.
The weirdos own this neighborhood for the
first time ever and they can't be kicked out.
That's beautiful. That's what this is all about.
For the first time, we now have digital communities
that can't be taken over, polished, sanitized, sterilized...
of any idea worthwhile and turned into a plaything
for Disney, McDonald's, Coca-Cola, JPMorgan Chase...
to shit all over the creativity and turn it
into nothing, into empty marketing slogans.
For the first time, we have digital
communities that can't be gentrified.
When people ask me, "Why are you excited
about cryptocurrencies? Aren't they weird?"
I say, "Yes! They're weird, they're beautifully weird.
That's why I'm interested in them."
My pledge, and the pledge of all the other people
who are in this because it's weird, is to keep it weird.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]